So good morning everyone, my name is Kai,
and I'm speaking to you from cold and rainy Maine this morning.
Like Ethel from our last section my focus is in computer science education as well,
so I'm presenting a recent project I did as I was finishing up my PhD last year.
So the motivation behind this project is that teaming is a core component in professional
software engineering. As pretty much all
software engineers work in teams, it is thus essential for undergraduate
computer science programs to teach students the skills of how to work effectively in a team
and how to to make valuable contributions despite the difficulty of splitting up a problem.
That being said,
there's some evidence that students may be inclined to free ride off of their peers
and then they receive a grade that does not correspond to their contributions -
they get credit for stuff that their - their teammates have done.
And I posit that much of the the difficulty with this is that,
or much of the reason for this, is that it's difficult to accurately
identify the contributions that students make to a team project,
particularly as the project gets bigger and as the team gets bigger.
And if teaching assistants struggle to identify what students have done,
they will struggle to give students helpful feedback on their contributions
and encourage students to make full contributions to the project.
And my - my question here, the central question,
I'll get down into the the details in a moment, is wondering if auto-generated summaries of what
the various members on a team have been up to are presented to teaching assistants,
can the TAs use this to get a better feel for the details of what each student has done
and then to give them feedback and grades according to this.
So the context I studied for this, was a sophomore level Java programming course
back at NC State University where I did my PhD. And this course features a lecture section that
has has four several-week projects associated with it
and then an associated lab section as well. And this is where students really learn the
collaborative work - the teamwork - as they work in teams of of three or
four students on these lab activities. And the way the course is set up is that
the lab grading is is mostly automated already through a whole bunch of scripts and use of
continuous integration platforms. Really,
the only thing that the the TAs grade manually is student code contributions
and then assessing whether the - the Java doc accurately describes the - the code in question.
So for the lab assignments students work in teams of three or four,
for three or four weeks at a stretch, at which point the teams are scrambled and
then this entire process repeats three times as the students complete a total
of 11 labs over the semester. So looking at what I studied in - in more detail,
my research questions were, first,
can automated contribution summaries help TAs grade assignments more quickly,
get through the process faster. And this I found basically, no.
Next, I considered
whether the - the contribution summaries can help TAs grade assignments more consistently,
more consistently identify what students have done than if they were unassisted
Third, I considered whether TAs prefer the grading
process when they have this to assist them, and finally whether it can help provide
students with better feedback, more actionable feedback that
they can use to figure out when they're sufficiently contributing to the team effort
and when they're not. So in order to answer these research questions,
I designed an algorithm that presents high level summaries of what each person on a team has done.
And the way it works is,
first it pulls metadata about a repository - things like commit hashes, timestamps,
authors, files changed, that sort of stuff - and tosses it into a database for later use.
Next, there
are two copies of the repository that are cloned.
And then for each of the - the changed files on each of the commits,
an abstract syntax tree is built representing the - the file before the commit and after the commit.
And I know that ASTs are sort of by definition abstract,
so an example to make it a little bit more concrete.
If we have a Java class that looks like this, it will boil down to the abstract syntax
tree we have over on the right side. And then if we make some changes to the class,
adding in a new field and a new method, we see some corresponding changes
to the abstract syntax tree. So the way that my algorithm works is,
it builds these ASTs from both revisions of the file
and then it will tree difference the ASTs to figure out what was added, changed,
or removed between the - the two versions. And then this is repeated for every file changed
on a commit and all commits within a time period, at which point the changes are binned or
summarized to get a high level view of what each person has been up to.
So to evaluate this algorithm and figure out if it helps TAs do a better job or not,
I recruited 13 former or current computer science TAs from my peers in the PhD program,
12 of whom had existing experience with grading team-based projects.
And then in my study I tasked them with,
first, grading some projects,
then evaluating and reflecting on some feedback from their peers in the study,
and then finally reflecting on the experience - on the study, on the contributions,
the contribution summaries they were provided. So in the first part of the study I tasked them
with grading a bunch of students assignments and I used a Google Sheets spreadsheet for
this just to to mimic the - the typical experience that they're familiar with.
And in the spreadsheet they were - they had rows corresponding to each of the repositories,
each of the projects they were to grade, and then columns with information
about what to do, so links to the automated
summaries for about half of the repositories, no automated summaries for the other half,
links to the the GitHub repositories so they could see all of the code,
the project history they were to look at, and then columns for them to fill in,
grades and feedback for the - the students whose projects they were grading.
So they filled this out for each of the three students on the team.
I've trimmed off students B and C so we only have A right here,
just to make it so we can actually read things. And then in part two of the study,
I asked TAs to reflect on some of the comments from their peers,
choose between pairs of comments that their peers had provided
on which one they felt was more actionable and they could do more with.
So to summarize what we learned at this point,
I found that the TAs grade projects much more consistently when they have the automated
contribution summaries to assist them compared to doing it entirely unassisted.
Yet at the same time the - the consistency, the inter-rater reliability - is pretty low,
so I use Krippendorff's alpha as a statistical test here,
and and Krippendorff argues for - for alpha values really of - of above 0.8 where possible,
and even with the contribution summaries to help them out,
TAs didn't quite hit this mark. So there's clearly future work still to
be done which I'll talk about momentarily. Next, in terms of whether the TAs would
actually choose to use this or not, because I'd come up with all the
shiniest tools in the world but if the TAs hate them it's not of much value,
I found that all of the participants preferred using the contribution summaries when grading
and 11 of the 13 strongly prefer them. And breaking them down on a - a feature
level I saw that the TAs found most of the features here to be pretty helpful,
both the simple information of just,
here's a list of commits of what each person has done,
and then the the more advanced stuff that came from my program analysis algorithm
and shows TAs where in the the project students have been involved.
And then finally in terms of results, getting back to the students,
I asked TAs to reflect on the - the feedback from their peers
and - and let me know which of the feedbacks - which - which feedback they thought
was more helpful, more actionable, and they considered that feedback from assignments
that had been graded with the automated contribution summaries was more actionable
than feedback that came from the manually graded assignments.
And additionally I found that the TAs give more partial credit as opposed to
full credit or no credit when they have the
contribution summaries available, which suggests that they're better able to - to
see nuance and identify partial contributions, as opposed to,
you've done basically nothing or you've done a bunch.
So that's sort of what I learned. As - as for, sort of, the implications of this,
despite a relatively small sample size - I only had just over a dozen participants in one two-hour
lab section where I ran the study - despite this,
the lab study still showed value to the contribution summary algorithm
in helping TAs identify what students have done and then give give them
grades and feedback accordingly. I'm doing a follow-on classroom study right now
where I'm trying to see, can this feedback actually help
students do better semester or - assignment on assignment over the course of a semester,
trying to see - do students find the feedback more actionable,
do they improve more over the course of the semester.
As for obvious future work,
there's obviously a lot more that will go into software engineering work than just Java code.
In terms of Python code, JavaScript code, but of course also non-code contributions,
the "everything else", the design, the project management,
the discussions around the water cooler that help the team work successfully.
So the open challenge remains, how do we account for everything else?
And I'm - I think a language agnostic AST analysis can get us part of the way there,
but there's still open questions on how do we account for the non-code contributions,
which is what I'm planning on pondering this
summer and figuring out what are the - the next steps we can take with this.
So to summarize what I did and what I learned from it,
I designed an algorithm that will present high-level summaries of what
students on teams or - or really anyone on a
team has contributed to their project and then I built it into a tool that works
on Java code tracked through GitHub and I did a quantitative lab
study where I demonstrated that the TAs who use this are able to
grade assignments more consistently, they prefer the grading process,
and I have tentative results suggesting the feedback to be more actionable,
more helpful to the students whose assignments are being graded.
So that's all I've got, but I would be delighted to take any questions at this point.
Great, thank you very much, Kai. Thank you.
First question coming in, so have you thought about
applying this to people doing code reviews in open source projects or in their jobs.
It seems like exactly the same summaries would be useful for somebody
who's about to dive into a large, you know, looking at a large pull request.
Amusingly my dad actually asked me the same question.
So he works at Salesforce and was was pondering whether this could be a useful thing
to see the changes made on a pull request and I've - I've considered it,
but not actually done any evaluation in that context.
Okay. The - the one the one
thing I think is is sort of dangerous here is, larger projects with more - more free-form
types of contributions that folks can make beyond just the Java code,
we want to make sure that people aren't having numbers being presented that look bad about them.
Maybe they're still making great contributions, they're doing all of the - the helping out the
newer members of the team, the big architecting stuff,
even if the the amount of code that they're doing is actually relatively small,
so I would want to make sure that, if I was going to use it in a different area,
that we're encouraging people to use it responsibly.
Okay, and another question that's come in,
do students use pair programming? Is there a way to take account of that?
In London Python dojos with similar team size you should try to have the least
experienced programmer at the keyboard. So the - the answer is, it depends.
Students are encouraged but not required to to do pair programming.
The way - the way that it works right now is that the - the
TAs will see a list of all of the commits and then in the commit message we hope, we - we
tell students to document in the commit message if they pair program.
My anecdotal evidence is that they do a lousy job of this,
so with - with limited documentation there's not a lot we can see,
but I have some planned work as well to maybe, give you -
I'm not - not figure out exactly what the numbers would look like,
how to weight things, but also to account for
these contributions at least where they can be discerned from commit messages.
So I have - I have some work in progress where I'm doing fuzzy matching on names and commit messages
and using that to figure out,
has someone else been involved in a pair programming effort,
and then we can account for that under their contributions too.